<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Viæ rectæ ad vitam longam, pars secunda VVherein the true vse of sleepe, exercise, excretions, and perturbations is, with their effects, discussed and applied to euery age, constitution of body, and time of yeare. By To: Venner Doctor of Physicke in Bathe.</title>
            <title>Via recta ad vitam longam. Part 2</title>
            <author>Venner, Tobias, 1577-1660.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1623</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 73 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 24 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A14333</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 24648</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S103044</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99838803</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99838803</idno>
            <idno type="VID">3192</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A14333)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 3192)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1398:5)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Viæ rectæ ad vitam longam, pars secunda VVherein the true vse of sleepe, exercise, excretions, and perturbations is, with their effects, discussed and applied to euery age, constitution of body, and time of yeare. By To: Venner Doctor of Physicke in Bathe.</title>
                  <title>Via recta ad vitam longam. Part 2</title>
                  <author>Venner, Tobias, 1577-1660.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[12], 30, [2] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by George Eld for George Winder, and are to be sold at his shop in St. Dunstans Church yard in Fleet-street,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1623.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Part 2 of: Via recta ad vitam longam.</note>
                  <note>Running title reads: Via recta ad vitam longam.</note>
                  <note>Includes index.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Central Library (Bristol, Eng.).</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Hygiene --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Longevity --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-12</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-12</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-02</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-02</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:3192:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>VIAE RECTAE <hi>AD</hi> VITAM LONGAM, PARS SECVNDA.</p>
            <p>VVherein the true vſe of Sleepe, Exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſe, Excretions, and Perturbations is, with their effects, diſcuſſed and ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plied to euery age, conſtitution of body, and time of yeare.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>BY</hi> TO: VENNER <hi>Doctor of Phyſicke in Bathe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by GEORGE ELD for GEORGE WINDER, and are to be ſold at his ſhop in S<hi rend="sup">t</hi>. <hi>Dunſtans</hi> Church yard in Fleet-ſtreet. 1623.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:3192:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:3192:2"/>
            <head>TO THE MOST EXCEL<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>LENT, ILLVSTRIOVS, AND Mighty Prince CHARLES, Prince of Wales, &amp;c.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">R</seg>IGHT Noble and moſt Illuſtrious Prince: Your gracious acceptance of my <hi>Via recta ad vitam lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gam,</hi> formerly conſecrated vnto you, induced me not a little to haſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>n the perfiting of the ſame, with the addition of a ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond Part, which I now likewiſe commend to your Highneſſe patronage, being a worke in regard of the ſubject moſt befitting your Majeſty, who is the chie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt hope and future health of Great-Britaines Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narchy. If theſe my Labours, that I may teſtifie my loyall and gratefull heart to your Maieſty, ſhall any way further your health and proſperity of body, I have my ayme and contentment. For without health <hi>Quid poteſt in hac vita eſſe gratum, quid jucun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dum?
<pb facs="tcp:3192:3"/>Non honor, non divitiae: imperfect a qui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dem ſunt omnia corporis bona, niſi ſecunda jun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gantur valetudine.</hi> Health therefore is the <hi>Sum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mum bonum</hi> in this life; <hi>quia vitam maximè ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cundam reddit &amp; foelicem.</hi> Wherefore that it may be obtained and enjoyed, <hi>Non tantummodo oran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dum, ſed &amp; enixè laborandum eſt.</hi> Thus refer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring both this Worke and myſelfe to your Highneſſe protection, with my daily prayers unto God for your Majeſties ſafety and happy continuance of life, to the exceeding great comfort of all true hearted Britaines, I in all dutifull obedience moſt humbly reſt</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>At your Highneſſe ſervice and command, To: VENNER.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:3192:3"/>
            <head>TO THE TRVLY <hi>GENEROVS AND</hi> Religious READERS, <hi>Health and Counſell.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">G</seg>Enerous and religious Readers; to you haue I heretofore written my <hi>Viam re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctam ad vitam longam;</hi> not to Ruſticks, or men of vile and ruſticke quality, who ſavour onely of the earth, and reſpect no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing leſſe then the welfare of their Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies; nor to any prophane, or ſeeming religious Patron of wicked and diſhonest perſons: But to you, I ſay, that are religious and truly generous, that maintaine your blood, and reputations by your noble and vertuous lives, have I written that Dieteticall Treatiſe: and now, in regard of your benigne Acceptance thereof (lightly eſteeming the ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liquity of ſome that are wiſe onely by inheritance, or that are of a detracting ſpirit) have perfected the ſame, with a Second part, for the preſeruation of your lives and health, which if yee will in any meaſure obſerue, <hi>Vos enim arctiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſimis regulis non obſtringo;</hi> I nothing doubt, but yee ſhall to Gods glory, your owne comfort, and good of your Countrey, live, a long, happy, and healthy life. But, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe
<pb facs="tcp:3192:4"/>it may happen, inregard of the great infirmity of Nature, in theſe laſt times, that yee may have ſome con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flicts with ſickneſſe, I will give you my advice therein, leſt being ſicke, and ſeeking remedy by Phyſicke, yee fall, as the old ſaying is, from <hi>Charybdis</hi> into <hi>Sylla,</hi> from one evill in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to another as bad, if not worſe. When yee are viſited with Sickneſse, yee muſt conſider that it is a ſymptome of your ſinne; and therefore firſt by humble confeſsion, and a peni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent heart make peace betwixt God and your Conſcience, and then ſend for the Phyſician: But for what Phyſician? not for the Mountebanke that deludes you with impoſtures; nor for the audacious Surgeon, that will take away your life, I meane your blood, upon every light occaſion; nor for the arrogant, and too too diſhonest Apothecary, that againſt conſcience, againſt the lawes, and againſt laudable and ancient cuſtomes, exerciſes Phyſicke, and growes inſolent with the Title of a Phyſician; nor for any other ſuch igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant Empericke, <hi>Qui And abatarum morè, clauſis ocu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lis, cum aegrotorum morbis pugnat, facir<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> per mortes experimenta;</hi> applying without any true reſpect had of the temperature, age, ſex, or time of yeare, one and the ſame re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>medy unto every one, as though every man had one and the ſame nature, and ſtate of body, or did labour in one and the ſame diſeaſe. But ſend for ſuch a Phyſician as is Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loſophically learned; that is honeſt, religious; that deales faithfully and diſcreetly with the ſicke, and that regards more the curing of the ſickneſſe, then the reward: ſuch an one, ſo often as yee haue occaſion, ſend for, loue, and enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine kindly, for hee will pray vnto the Lord, that he would proſper that which hee giveth for your eaſe and remedy. I cannot but here taxe ſome Phyſicians; I wiſh there were no ſuch <hi>Spurii</hi> amongst us, more baſe and inhumane then
<pb facs="tcp:3192:4"/>the baſeſt Mechanicks, who, <hi>Canino more,</hi> abide not men of their owne ranke and quality, but hate and detract them; and yet theſe great Worthies,<note place="margin">A Note of baſeneſs, if not alſo of inſufficien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy.</note> out of what humour judge yee, not onely Fidler-like hang after the heeles of great men, to bee ſet a worke, and inſinuate with Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>women (working vpon their light credulent nature) telling them, That their skill, for curing their infirmities, tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcends other men; but alſo become &amp; collogue with baſe and unworthy people to have their alarum of praiſe. Among Phyſicians, theſe I ſuppoſe are they that reſpect their owne gaine more then the glory of God, or the good of the Patient, and therefore very worthy to bee exploded, <hi>Ex Medico<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum albo.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>What ſhall I ſay of ſome Divines, who <hi>(Salva ſancti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>orum reverentia)</hi> beſides the cure of Soules, take upon them the cure of bodies, becauſe the Ocean of ſacred <hi>Theo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logie</hi> is not ſufficient for their ſwelling braines, and perhaps puffed up with Quinteſſences. <hi>Quid illis cum Medicina?</hi> Let them looke to the Charge that Saint <hi>PAVL</hi> giueth unto them. Verely,<note place="margin">2 Tim. c. 4. v. 1, 2.5.</note> I wonder how they can bee inſenſible of the great burthen of Soules that lye upon them, for which in the great and terrible day of accompts, they muſt give accompt; and then, when not onely the actions of all men,<note place="margin">Exech. 28.8.</note> but alſo the very ſecret motions and intentions of the heart ſhall bee made manifeſt; what will theſe halfe-curing Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſicians of Soules and bodies doe, when they ſhall bee queſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oned, not ſo much for how many bodies they haue cured; perhaps for how many they have ſent packing to <hi>Sheol</hi> by their importune and prepoſterous phyſicke, as for how many Soules they have cured and purged from the filth of ſinno and iniquity, by their diligent miniſtery of the ſacred Word, and converted unto God.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:3192:5"/>
            <p>But as for Women that with much temerity, take up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on them to give and preſcribe medicines, and the ſame not of the meaneſt ranke neither, as though Phyſicke, the moſt myſticall and nobleſt of all Arts, were ſubject to their ſhal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low and precipitate apprehenſion (reverence to thoſe Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tlewomen, that binde up <hi>Lazarus</hi> ſoares, and refreſh them with the fragments that fall from their Tables) I muſt tell them, that if they doe it out of pure charity, it is ſinfull, becauſe there is error in the action; if out of any vaine glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, it is more ſinfull; if out of a deſire of gaine, it is moſt ſinfull: Of all which, our poly-pragmaticall Miniſters in all likelihood, that cannot containe themſelves within the limits of their owne callings, goe not free and unfaultie. <hi>Marcilius Ficinus,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Lib. de Trip. vita Apolog.</note> a Prieſt, and well learned in the my<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteries of Phyſicke, endeauoring to prove the lawfulneſſe for Divines to exerciſe Phyſicke, concludes that they muſt doe it, <hi>Charitatis gratia,</hi> for charities ſake. And is not this thinke you, the marke that our practicall Miniſters ayme at? I will not condemne all; but ſo many of them as I know, deale in phyſicke, as they doe ſometimes for a Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonage, they take not fees <hi>directè,</hi> like Phyſitians; but <hi>in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>directè,</hi> under the name of a Druggie medicine, or per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps a ſtrange elaborated Quinteſſence, exhauſt the pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ents purſe much more then the generous and learned Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſician. And if you will looke into their lives, you ſhall finde ſome of them to be prophane; others, eſpecially thoſe whoſe braines ſwell, and are overheated with Quinteſſences, to be heady, proud, contentious; and yet after a puritanicall fury, holy. To the beſt of them, I ſay as Saint <hi>PAVL</hi> did to <hi>Archippus: Take heed to your Miniſterie.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>If the beſt learned, and ſuch as bend their whole forces thereunto are but ſufficient to undertake the practice of
<pb facs="tcp:3192:5"/>Phyſicke, what ſhall bee judged of the rabblement of Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perickes, and other unworthy and diſtracted Practicioners? Well, the time will come, when wee ſhall be all convented to yeeld an account for all our actions, wee ſhall not bee a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to conceale any of them from God, at whoſe name wee ſhould tremble, the great Iudge of all the world, to whom the very ſecret motions of our hearts are manifeſt, and who will reward every man according to his worke. Know then, whatſoever thou art, that it is not all gaine that is gotten, except it be well gotten, and with a good conſcience; which I wiſh all men, and by name, ſuch as uſurpe the practice of Phyſick, to the ruine &amp; hurt of many, to lay to their hearts, as a cordiall Antidot againſt all unlawfull gaine, and bee reformed.</p>
            <p>But is the fault altogether in them that uſurpe the pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctice of Phyſicke? No verely; It is as much, if not more, in the abſurdity of them that expoſe their bodies they care not to whom; and if they chance, through the benefit of nature and a ſtrong conſtitution, to recover; or for that, the cauſe of the infirmity was formerly by ſome learned Phyſician re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moved, as it oftentimes happens, a great cure is wrought, the report whereof, with the light vulgar, and other baſe minded people, is ſo prevalent, as that it is able to raiſe one from being a pariſh Clarke, to the title of a great Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſician; and yet all this while, the Cure, if there were any, was but accidentally, raſhly, or prepoſterouſly effected, to the great injury of nature, and ſhortning of the dayes, though the ignorant Patient vnderſtand it not. But if the Cure, or rather the Hurt, ſhall by an out-landiſh Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ricke, or Surgeon, that <hi>apud nos,</hi> turnes Phyſician, and that no meane one neither, bee effected, the more admira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble. For verely, ſuch is the inconſtancy, folly, and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſneſſe
<pb facs="tcp:3192:6"/>verſneſſe of moſt our people, that a Phyſician, how learned and honeſt ſoever, and bleſſed of God in his courſes, can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not, vnleſſe hee bee Outlandiſh, or at least in his birth and education, altogether a ſtranger and remote, bee in any good eſteeme with them, for they muſt have phyſicke from farre, <hi>Nihil praetioſum domi:</hi> the proverbiall ſaying is not more ancient then true, <hi>Rara ſunt chara: Sed mun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dus vult decipi, &amp; decipiatur.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The men of this world are, in their worldly affaires, wiſe, and doe with the <hi>Chinoys,</hi> ſee with both eyes, and will, rather then loſe one foote of land, retaine the beſt counſell that can bee had; but when their health, <hi>quae cum om<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nibus mundi copiis non eſt commutanda,</hi> ſhall by ſick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe bee called into queſtion, an illiterated Empericke, a peremptorie uſurping Apothecary, an ambitious Surgeon, ſcarſe the ſuperſicies of a Phyſician, perhaps a pariſh Clarke, or a ſorcering Horſe-leach, or any other of what condition ſoever, whether Inſidell or Chriſtian, whether vertuous, or full of all impiety, it matters not, is a Phyſician meet enough to encounter with ſickneſſe, death's Champion. <hi>O genus hominum inſulſum, quibus Helleborum porri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gendum, ut purgato cerebro deſinant delirare.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Dolendum ſanè in Repub. literata,</hi> that the noble Art of Phyſicke, ſhould by the toleration of unworthy Practi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cioners be diſgraced, and the people hurt. Wee have lawes to prevent this evill, <hi>utinam vitam habuiſſent,</hi> I wiſh they had their due execution; but I doubt not, but that our moſt gratious &amp; learned <hi>SOVERAIGNE</hi> wil, at length, caſt an eye of reformation and reſpect upon the diſgraced fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culty of Phyſicke, which Kings and Princes in former times, by their owne proper ſtudies greatly graced, and repreſſe ſuch, as under colour of helping, deſtroy many of his peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple,
<pb facs="tcp:3192:6"/>
               <hi>abſ<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> poenae metu;</hi> and ſo reduce the noble Art of phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſicke no its ancient ſplendor and dignity; as it is to be ſeene at this day in ſome well governed Common-weales in that reſpect.</p>
            <p>But, having taxed divers, I muſt looke to have ſome ſcandalous and malicious imputations caſt upon my ſelfe, not onely from them that are taxed, but alſo from a Grand <hi>Caitiffe-fordian Momus,</hi> who with his Foule Mouth, and Doggiſh Teeth, hath mightily defamed mee, and delacera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted the former Impreſsions of my <hi>Via recta ad vitam lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gam.</hi> As for the former ſort I paſſe not, I have delivered my minde freely, and I know I ſpeake the truth; and if I ſhould bee commended of One that is full of all impiety, that is a common Rayler, Slanderer, and Detractor, and under whoſe lippes is the poyſon of Aſps, I ſhould cry out, <hi>Quid mali feci?</hi> But I, lightly regarding the obliquity of ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>levolent and detracting Spirits, conclude with the honeſt Reader; to whom I wiſh theſe my labours very profitable.</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>
                  <date>
                     <hi>APRIL 22. 1603.</hi>
                  </date>
               </dateline>
               <salute>Vale, Et ſis mihi, ut ego tibi.</salute>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:3192:7"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:3192:7"/>
            <head>VIAE RECTAE AD VITAM LONGAM <hi>PARS SECVND A.</hi>
            </head>
            <div n="1" type="section">
               <head>Of Sleepe and VVatching. SECT. I.</head>
               <head type="sub">That Sleepe may be taken for the health of the body, how many things ought ſuch as are ſtudious of their health to obſerve therein?</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">F</seg>Oure: Firſt, the Time; ſecondly, the Place; thirdly, the Poſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture or lying of the body; and fourthly, the quantity of Sleepe. Of all which in their order. But firſt I will ſet downe the commodities of moderate and ſeaſonable ſleepe, which next to nouriſhments that ſuſtaine the body, is moſt profitable and neceſſary: For it helpeth the digeſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,<note place="margin">The commodi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties of ſleepe.</note> recreateth the mind, repaireth the ſpirits, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forteth and refreſheth the whole body, and is for all crudities even a preſent remedy: for it concocteth
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:3192:8"/>not onely the meats, but alſo the humours; and the reaſon of all which is, becauſe in all the time of ſleepe, the animall faculty is at reſt, but the naturall is in the ſtronger action, by reaſon of the regreſſe of the heat into the inner parts, and therefore it is that the beſt concoction is made in ſleepe. Moreover, by the returne of the heat into the inner parts, the vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tall faculty is much ſtrengthned, becauſe the heart is then abundantly ſupplied with blood for breeding of ſpirit.<note place="margin">The three prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipall faculties are greatly hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen &amp; refreſhed by ſleepe.</note> From whence it appeareth, how ſleepe ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth much for the three principall faculties of the body: for by it the braine is moiſtned, the animall ſpirits quieted and refreſhed, the ſtomacke and liver for concoction, and the heart for ingendring of ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, fortified and aſſiſted.</p>
               <p>Now for the order of ſleepe, wherein, as I have ſaid, foure things are to be obſerved. And firſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the time for ſleeping and waking, wee muſt follow the courſe of Nature, that is, to wake in the day, and ſleepe in the night: <hi>Dies enim vigilie, nox ſomno dicata eſt.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Why the night is moſt conve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nient for ſleepe.</note> For the Sun by his radiant beames illuminating our Hemiſphere, openeth the pores of the body, and dilateth the humours and ſpirits from the Center to the circumferent parts, which to wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king and neceſſary actions doth excite and naturally prouoke. But on the contrary, when the Sunne de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parteth from our Hemiſphere all things are coarcta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, and the ſpirits returne into the bowels and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt parts of the body, which naturally invite to ſleepe. Wherefore if we pervert the order of Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, as to ſleepe in the day, and wake in the night, we violently reſiſt the motion of Nature, for ſleepe
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:3192:8"/>draweth the naturall heat inward, and the heat of the day draweth it outward, ſo that there is made as it were, a fight and combat with Nature to the ruine of the body. Yet ſuch as, by reaſon of a weake and ſick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly diſpoſition of body, doe take vnquiet or little reſt in the night, or are otherwiſe by extraordinary and neceſſary occaſions hindred, may well ſleepe in the morning <hi>adprimam partem diei,</hi> that is, till nine of the clocke, but to ſleepe afterwards is not ſo whole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome, eſpecially at afternoones, as ſhall be hereafter ſhewed.</p>
               <p>But why the night is moſt conuenient for ſleepe, two other reaſons alſo may bee well aſſigned. The firſt is the naturall moiſture and ſilence of the night, which for ſleepe is very conducible. The other is the ſufficiencie of time, not onely for the full and abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lute concoction of the meats, but alſo of ſuperfluous humours, which the night doth afford, and that by reaſon of the regreſſe of the heat and ſpirits into the inward and digeſtive parts. They therefore that a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt nature vitiouſly uſe the night for the day, and the day for the night, <hi>tanquam noctuae,</hi> are here juſtly to be reproued: and ſo are alſo ſtudents,<note place="margin">Vntimely was chings moſt pernitious to Students.</note> to whom vntimely watchings are moſt pernicious, that with night ſtudies macerate themſelves, exhauſt their ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits, and acquire a poore weake melancholicke ſtate of body For all parts of the body, eſpecially the chiefeſt being wearied and weakned with labour in the day, the night approching, deſire reſt; and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore then if by ſtudy and untimely watching they are deprived of their refreſhing, and the ſpirits retra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted from the ſtomacke and principall parts, weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:3192:9"/>muſt needs follow, and a bad concoction, and the body conſequently repleted with crude, putride, and vaporous humours. Wherefore I adviſe Stu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dents that muſt of neceſſity ſometimes watch and ſtudy by night, that they doe it not till after their firſt ſleepe: for in that ſpace the concoctions of the ſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mack and liver are moſt commonly effected, and the wearied parts in ſome meaſure refreſhed.</p>
               <p>Wherefore here by the way I adviſe all men, eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially ſuch as are charged with publicke buſineſſe of importance, that they carefully obſerve to goe to their bed with a quiet and free mind:<note place="margin">Three things neceſſary to quiet ſleepe.</note> for that the ſleepe may bee peaceable and comfortable, three things are neceſſary; a temperate braine, a ſweet va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pour, and a quiet mind. If therefore ye deſire peace<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able and comfortable reſt, live ſoberly, eſchew cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dity, and embrace tranquility of mind.</p>
               <p>But if honeſt occaſions, beſides an ill diſpoſition of body, ſhall occaſion watching in the beginning of the night, let thy ſupper bee ſlender, and make a mends by ſleeping ſo much the longer in the mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning. But I wiſh ſuch as tender their healths, eſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally Students, not to addict themſelues to morning ſleepe, but by all meanes to ſhunne and avoid the occaſion thereof, for he that ſleepes in the morning when he ought to ariſe and ſtirre his body that all parts may the better expurge their exerements de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained in ſleepe,<note place="margin">The great diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>commodity of morning ſleep.</note> by ſleeping in the morning hinders their expulſion, which occaſioning obſtructions and noy ſome vapours, greatly offend the head, dull the ſenſes, and is very pernicious to the whole body.</p>
               <p>Here ſome may deſire to know whether it bee al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>together
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:3192:9"/>vnwholeſome to ſleepe after dinner. Whereunto I anſwer, that ſleeping at noones is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned as moſt hurtfull to the body, becauſe it over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moiſtneth the braine,<note place="margin">The diſcommo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dities of ſlee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping at noones.</note> and filleth the head full with vaporous ſuperfluities. And the reaſon why it filleth the head with ſuperfluous moiſture, is, becauſe the night hath ſufficiently moiſtned it, as that it needeth not to be moiſtned againe by ſleepe in the day, but ought rather to be dryed by watchings and motions of the body. And from hence it is that ſleeping at noones cauſeth heavineſſe of the head, dulneſſe of wit, diſtillations, defluxions of humours, lethargies. and other cold diſeaſes of the braine, and palſies, by relaxing the ſinewes. Moreover it hurteth the eyes, ſpoileth the colour, puffeth up the Spleene with winde, maketh the body unluſty, and prepareth it for Fevers and Impoſtumes. Yet notwithſtanding all theſe hurts which are incident to them that will needs ſleepe in the day time,<note place="margin">Sleeping at noones not to be prohibited at all times, nor to all bodies.</note> ſleeping at noones is not al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes, nor to all bodies to be prohibited, ſo as it be admitted with the cautions hereafter aſſigned. For if the night ſhall be unquiet, or without ſleepe, or the body wearied with extraordinary labour, or the ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits exhauſted, and the ſtrengths dejected by immo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derate and exceſſive heat, as it oftentimes chanceth in the hot ſeaſons of the yeare, it is not amiſſe to ſleepe at noones: for by it the ſpirits are collected into the inner parts, the mind freed of cogitati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and the whole body conſequently very much re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>freſhed. Moreover, ſuch as are leane, and of an hot and dry temperature of body, may well ſleepe at noones, becauſe it greatly refreſheth their bodies by
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:3192:10"/>recalling their ſoone vaniſhing ſpirits. And that it is lawfull at any time of the yeare for old men to ſleepe a nap at noones, by reaſon of their imbecil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity, needs no demonſtration.<note place="margin">Sleeping at noones hurtfull to all corpu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent bodies.</note> But the Phlegma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticke, ſanguine, and all corpulent bodies muſt be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ware how they ſleepe at noones, for it is better for ſuch to macerate themſelves a little, by abſtaining from ſleepe, then by it to be turgide and puffed up. Wherefore in the hot ſeaſons of the yeare it is good for them after dinner to reſt themſelves for the ſpace of an houre in a cold bower free from all care and cogitation, which reſt verely is no leſſe profitable to them, then an houres ſleepe for dry, leane, and exte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuated bodies.</p>
               <p>But that ſleeping at noones may bee admitted with the greater profit and leſſe detriment,<note place="margin">Five conditions to be obſerved in ſleeping at noones.</note> five con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditions are diligently to be obſerued therein. The firſt is that it be not taken immediately after dinner, but an houre after, or halfe an houre at the leaſt, in which ſpace it is good to walke a little, that the meat may the better deſcend into the ſtomacke, for then fewer vapours will aſcend and offend the head. The ſecond is, that it be taken not lying, but rather ſit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting with the body upright, becauſe the head will be the leſſe offended with vapours aſcending unto it. The third is, that it be not overlong, not above halfe an houre, or an houre at the moſt, that the heat may be onely collected from the outward parts, for ſo ſhort ſleep cannot replete the head with vapours, and in the meane while the concoction is ſufficiently holpen, the ſtrengths refreſhed, and any heavineſſe of the head removed. The fourth is, that it bee not
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:3192:10"/>taken in an hot place, but rather enclining to cold, eſpecially in the ſummer, for to ſleepe in an hot place is very hurtfull, as ſhall be by and by ſhewed. The fift is, that the awakening be not ſudden, but with good moderation, to prevent the diſtraction of the ſpirits. And thus much for the time of ſleepe.</p>
               <p>Concerning the place moſt convenient for ſleep,<note place="margin">What place is moſt conveni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent for ſleepe.</note> it muſt be ſomewhat darke, and defended from the light, eſpecially of the Moone by night, which en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſeth rheumes, temperate in heat and cold, yea rather inclining to cold then heat; for to ſleepe in an hot place is very dangerous, cauſing faintneſſe, and oftentimes ſwounding vpon the awaking, by reaſon of the contrary motions of ſleepe, and the ambient heat of the place. For the ſpirits and natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall heat, which by meanes of ſleepe are drawne in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward, are by the heat without contrariwiſe drawne outward. Wherefore the place for ſleepe ought to be very cloſe, and above all not dampiſh, for that is moſt pernicious to the body, and eſpecially to the head. And although the place for ſleepe muſt rather encline to cold then heat, yet our bodies while wee ſleepe muſt with cloathes, according as the conſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tution of the aire ſhall require, be ſufficiently cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, leſt that while the naturall heat is within about digeſtion, the outward parts be offended with cold. But the chiefeſt care muſt bee of the head, that in ſleepe it take not cold, which will occaſion palſies,<note place="margin">The head and necke in ſleepe muſt carefully be defended from cold.</note> and other affects of the braine and ſinewes; and yet too much covering weakens and offends the head. The necke alſo in ſleepe muſt not be neglected, for the well wrapping thereof is a ſpeciall remedy
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:3192:11"/>againſt nocturnall rheumes, and therefore I wiſh all Students diligently to obſerve the uſe thereof.</p>
               <p>Concerning the manner of lying while we ſleepe,<note place="margin">What poſiture of the body is beſt in ſleepe.</note> the beſt is on the right ſide, or on the left, with the hands, legges, and necke, yea and the whole body a little bowed, eſpecially in the winter, for encrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing the heat of the bowels. But if you deſire to know whether it be beſt to lye firſt on the right ſide, or on the left: I anſwer, that it is beſt to lye firſt on the left ſide, that the meats may the better deſcend to the bottome of the ſtomacke, which toward the left ſide is chiefly ſituated, and the alimentary juice be the more eaſily conveied to the Liver: and after the firſt ſleep to turn to the right ſide; for this change doth greatly eaſe the body, and helpe the conco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction and diſtribution. The head muſt be ſomewhat high, well bolſtred up, for the better deſcenſion and concoction of the meats.</p>
               <p>Having ſet downe the beſt poſiture of the body in ſleepe,<note place="margin">VVhether ſlee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping upright upon the back, or groveling upon the belly, be altogither unwholeſome.</note> I will examine whether lying upright upon the backe, or groveling upon the belly in ſleepe, be altogether unwholeſome. As for ſleeping upright upon the backe, it is altogether unwholeſome, for ſo many as ſleepe after that faſhion, have unpleaſant and troubleſome ſleeps, and are for the moſt part ſubject to the paſſion which we call the Night-mare, the palſie, lethargy, crampe, and ſuch like diſeaſes of the braine and ſinewes. And that not without cauſe, for lying upon the backe cauſeth the ſuperflu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous matter of the head to encline and fall into the hinder part of the braine, where is the originall of the motory ſinewes, and by that meanes the ſpirits
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:3192:11"/>being ſtopped, the aforeſaid maladies are eaſily en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gendered. Moreover, lying upon the backe, hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth the reynes, and maketh them ſubject to obſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction; and therefore I wiſh all ſuch as are ſubject to the ſtone, carefully to ſhunne that manner of ſlee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping.</p>
               <p>Concerning ſleeping upon the belly,<note place="margin">To ſleepe upon the belly, when, and for what bodies profita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble.</note> that may be ſomtimes tolerable, yea very neceſſary, when winde ſhall afflict the belly, or the ſtomacke be overchar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged with meat; for by that poſiture, the naturall heat is retayned and increaſed in the bowells, whereby the Stomacke for concoction is much comforted, and the torments of the belly greatly mitigated: Wherefore it is verie profitable for ſuch as have fee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble digeſtion, and are troubled with winde, to lye and ſleepe ſometimes groveling upon the belly; but it may hurt the ſight, by cauſing the humours to flow unto the eyes: and therefore ſuch, whoſe eies are feeble, or are ſubject to a defluxion of humours into them, muſt very carefully eſchew this manner of ſleeping.</p>
               <p>But it is worth the inquiry,<note place="margin">VVhether it bee expedient to ſleepe with the mouth a little open.</note> whether it be good to ſleepe with the mouth a little open. Some there are that altogether deny it; But I approve the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary, and that for three reaſons. The firſt is, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the breath paſſeth more freely, and the fuligi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nous fumes better breathed forth and diſcuſſed: and hence it is, that ſuch as ſleepe with their mouth o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen, have their breath leſſe corrupted; whereas of the contrary, they that ſleep with their mouth cloſe, have commonly an ill breath, and foule teeth. The ſecond is, becauſe ſome rheumaticke moyſture may
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:3192:12"/>in ſleepe paſſe forth at the mouth, which if it ſhould bee ſhut, would fall upon the Lungs, to their great offence. The third reaſon is, becauſe through the deſcent of rheume, from the head to the noſtrils, the free paſſage of the breath through them may be let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted; whereupon, unleſſe wee ſleepe with the mouth ſomewhat open, ſnorings, offenſive rowtings, and oftentimes untimely awakings doe enſue. Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore I conclude, that it is good to ſleepe with the mouth ſomewhat open, eſpecially, for them that are ſubject to the rheume. And becauſe the tongue, pallat, and gums of ſuch as ſleepe with their mouth open, are commonly after ſleepe very drie, and affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted alſo with ſlimie matter adhering to them; but to this later, thoſe that ſleep with their mouth cloſe are moſt ſubject:<note place="margin">The waſhing and cleanſing of the mouth after ſleepe ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry neceſſary.</note> I adviſe, that all men in the mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nings after their ſleep, waſh well their mouth, gums, and teeth with fountaine water, roſe water, and a little vinegar mixed together, wherein a few Sage leaves, and Cloves ſliced have bin ſteeped all the night, by gargling it in their mouths: for it tempe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth the drineſſe of the mouth, cleanſeth away the ſlimie ſuperfluities, and maketh the breath ſweet, which in ſleepe, by reaſon of fuliginous vapours that ariſe from the Stomacke, is moſt commonly cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupted. Where, by the way, it is to bee advertiſed, that their breath is moſt tainted in ſleepe that are ſubject to obſtructions; wherfore ſuch bodies ought to bee purged and purified, according as the affected parts ſhall require.</p>
               <p>Concerning the quantity or time how long wee ſhould ſleepe,<note place="margin">How long wee ſhould ſleepe.</note> it cannot bee certainly alike defined
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:3192:12"/>for all men, wherein, no doubt, a mediocritie, as in all other things, yet limited with many circumſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, is beſt. It muſt be meaſured by health and ſick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, by age, by emptineſſe or fulneſſe of the body, and by the complexion. And, becauſe the concocti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, which is the root of life, is ſpecially furthered by ſleep, we muſt obſerve to ſleep till the concoctio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s in the ſtomacke &amp; liver are finiſhed. But to know when the coconctions are compleat and ended, it is to be diſcerned upon the awaking, by the ſenſible lightnes of all the body, eſpecially of the head, and paſſage downe of the meate from the ſtomacke, and the cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine defire to avoide urine, and to goe to the ſtoole, ſo neither of them bee extraordinarily procured by error of diet, or otherwiſe. Contrariwiſe,<note place="margin">The whole time of ſleepe being divided into 3 parts, the firſt is chiefly profitable to the ſtomacke, the ſecond to the ſtomacke and liuer, the third, <hi>in qua ſegregatio fit puri ab impu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ro,</hi> to the heart and the braine.</note> heavineſs in the body and eyes, and ſavour of the meat before eaten, ſignifie, that the ſleepe is not ſufficient. From whence it may well bee concluded, that for ſuch as are healthfull, &amp; in their youthfull and conſtant age, ſeven or eight houres is a ſufficient time for the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinuance of ſleepe, becauſe in them the concoctions are in that ſpace commonly perfected. But ſuch as are weake and ſickly by nature, require a longer time of reſt, as nine, ten, or eleven houres, for helping the concoction, and reſtoring the ſtrengths.</p>
               <p>The like is to be ſaid of old men,<note place="margin">Somnus ſenibus vitaeſt, vigilia ruina.</note> for whom ſleepe verely is ſo profitable, that, becauſe it chiefly hel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peth the concoction, whereupon plenty of nouriſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able moiſture doth follow, nothing, next to meats of good juyce, is ſo available for repayring their de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cayed ſtate of Body. Children alſo, that have not attained to the age of eighteene yeares, require lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:3192:13"/>ſleepe then youth and middle age, that immo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derate fluxion of vaporous moyſture by the pores, whereunto they are by reaſon of their lax and tender skinne, moſt ſubject, may bee hindred, and their growth conſequently bettered and encreaſed.</p>
               <p>But withall, there muſt alwaies in every age be ſpeciall reſpect had of the complexion;<note place="margin">VVhy doe cho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lericke and me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lancholicke bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies require longer ſleepe then the phleg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maticke or ſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guine?</note> for Chole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ricke and Melancholicke Bodies need longer ſleepe then the Phlegmaticke or Sanguine, that the acri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monie of Choller may be tempered, and the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coction holpen: For, to drie and leane bodies ſuch as are the Cholericke and Melancholicke, nothing is more wholſome then quiet and ſound ſleepe, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe by it, the parts are generally moiſtened and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>freſhed, both in that it helpeth the concoction, as alſo, becauſe it letteth the difflation and waſting of the humors.<note place="margin">VVholſome counſell for co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lericke and me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lancholicke bodies.</note> And, becauſe that to leane Cholericke and Melancholicke Bodies, nothing is more pernici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous then too much watchfulneſſe, whereunto, by reaſon of their drie diſpoſition of body, they are ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry ſubject; I adviſe, that they uſually obſerve, eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially in the hot ſeaſons of the yeare, to drinke at their going to bed, a good draught of a ſoporife<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous Almond milke, made with the decoction of ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>corticated Barley well mundified and abluted, Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuce, the flowers of Borage and Violets, or in ſtead of them, the freſheſt leaves, and let it alſo have a lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle choiſe Roſe water, and bee dulcorated or ſweet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned with the fineſt ſugar: for this drinke excellently moiſteneth and tempereth the braine, procureth ſleepe, and refreſheth the whole bodie. The emul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of the ſeeds of white Poppie, may alſo verie pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fitable
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:3192:13"/>to bee added thereunto.</p>
               <p>But, of the contrary, to the Phlegmaticke and ſuch as are drowſie through the exceſſe of moyſture,<note place="margin">Little ſleepe beſt for phleg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maticke and groſſe bodies.</note> watchings are to bee commended and enjoyned, <hi>quia deſiccant &amp; attenuant,</hi> leſt that much ſleepe, or longer then is convenient onely for concoction, ſhould increaſe their moiſt and cold diſtemperature, and make it altogether ſickly.</p>
               <p>As for the Sanguine, their ſleepe muſt be very moderate, not above ſeven howers at the moſt;<note place="margin">VVhy muſt the ſanguine be ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry wary of im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moderate ſleepe?</note> for they are very apt to bee groſſe, which much ſleepe, or more then is fitting for their temperature, will ſoone occaſion. Wherefore it is better for them to bee ſparing in ſleepe, and to bee ſomewhat macera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted with watchings, then to be exceedingly puffed up therewith. Doe wee not finde by daily experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, that thoſe which are more indulgent of their bellies and ſleepe then is meete, become ſo corpu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent, groſſe and ill favoured, that their breaſt and chinne even meet together: wherefore it is no mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vell that they become unhealthfull and unluſtie in their bodies, ſtupid and dull in their wits.<note place="margin">The diſcommo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dityes of immo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derate ſleepe and watchings.</note> To con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude this Section, as Sleepe, unleſſe it bee mode<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate, and in fit time admitted, weakens the naturall heat, burdens the head with vapors, detaines the excrements longer then is meete; in a word, makes men ſluggiſh, lumpiſh and unhealthfull, heavie hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, of no wit or memorie. So watching, except it bee with mediocrity, dryeth up and conſumeth the bodie, dimineth the ſight, waſteth the Spirits, and deſtroyeth all the powers and faculties both of body and minde. Let therefore both the ſleep and watch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:3192:14"/>bee ſeaſonable and moderate; without which gratefull and amiable viciſſitude, our condition were miſerable, and life not to bee preſerved.</p>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>Whether drying and warming of the bed, <hi>Pelueignito,</hi> a little before the entring thereinto, bee expedient and neceſſary? And what is to bee done after the ſleepe, for the health of the body, before wee betake our ſelves to our ordinary and neceſſary buſineſſe?</head>
                  <p>SOme Captious, Scoffing, and Caitiffe-ſordian-like Momus, will perhaps ſuppoſe theſe two <hi>Quaeres</hi> to bee idle and ſuperſluous; but I, lightly regarding His obliquity, doe, for the good of them to whom I write this Treatiſe, follow my method, and adde them as an Appendix to this Section. To the former therefore I anſwer, that for Students, for the Aged, and all ſuch as are weake by nature, and that lead a tender and delicate courſe of life, the cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtome of warming the bed, is for two reaſons very expedient and neceſſary in the cold &amp; moiſt ſeaſons of the yeare. The firſt is, that the Body, upon put<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting off the garments, may not on a ſodaine be affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted with the externall cold. The ſecond is, becauſe the interiour heat is comforted by the externall, the concoction holpen, and all ſuperfluous moyſture the better conſumed. But I approve not this cuſtome to ſuch as are healthfull, and ſtrong, becauſe it will debilitate their Bodies, and make them over nice and effeminate. It remaineth therefore, that it is on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly convenient for Students, for the Aged, and all ſuch as are weake and tender by nature.</p>
                  <pb n="15" facs="tcp:3192:14"/>
                  <p>To the ſecond I anſwer, that after you have ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken ſufficient and competent reſt, it is good, before you ariſe out of your Bed, that you gently rub and ſtroake downward your breaſts and ſides; but your necke, ſhoulders, backe, armes, hand-wriſts, pin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bones,<note place="margin">Frications.</note> thighes and legges more ſtrongly with your owne hand, or with an hot linnen cloath, doubled and heated for the purpoſe, or cauſe them to be rub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bed, becauſe it quickeneth the Blood, and ſtreng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theneth the parts, by exciting the naturall heate. When you are riſen, and before alſo, extend and ſtretch out your armes, legges, and whole body, that the animall ſpirits may bee dilated to the exteriour parts; and the limbes by that meanes corroborated: then walke a little up and downe, that the ſuperflui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties which ſhall bee in the ſtomacke and other parts, may the more ſpeedily deſcend and bee avoyded; and bee very diligent to excrete the Vrine, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe the excrements of the Belly; and let not with leſſe diligence the ſuperfluities of the noſe by exſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flation, and of the breaſt by expectoration bee pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged forth: for nothing is more hurtfull to the Body then the retention of the excrements. That done, waſh and plunge your eies in cold water, for that not onely cleanſeth away the filth, but alſo cleareth and preſerveth the ſight. And let the mouth bee cleanſed with cold water, and a little vinegar added thereto, and the gummes and teeth rubbed with a Sage leafe or two dipped therein, or waſhed and cleanſed with the infuſion aforeſhewed; and after rub the teeth hard with a courſe dry cloath: for this purifieth the breath, and preſerveth the teeth from
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:3192:15"/>corruption. Then let your head bee well combed, that the pores may bee opened, to avoide ſuch va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pours as yet by ſleepe are not conſumed. And in the cold and moyſt ſeaſons of the yeare, let the head al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo be well rubbed with a courſe linnen cloath, ſom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what heated: for therby the naturall heat is excited, the pores opened, vaporous and rheumaticke ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fluities diſcuſſed and difflated,<note place="margin">Rubbings of the head and necke mornings with an hot cloath, very effectuall againſt rheums and cold infir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mities of the ſinewes.</note> and conſequently, the braine and animall ſpirits exceedingly comfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted. Of this therefore, as alſo of rubbing the necke in like manner, I wiſh Students, and all ſuch as are ſubject to rheumes, palſies, and ſuch like affects of the ſinewes, to have a ſpeciall care.</p>
                  <p>All which being done for the body, let not your better part paſſe neglected, but before you be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>take your ſelfe to your ſtudie, or ſuch buſineſs as your place ſhall require, conſecrate halfe an houre at the leaſt unto Almightie GOD, by pouring forth your thankefull ſoule unto him, for his gracious prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cting you from infinite dangers and calamities that might have bin befallen you untill this preſent time, with a true confeſſion of your ſinnes, with an hearty and unfained repentance for them, and with a ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cere and ſetled purpoſe and determination for the amendment of your life in that poore and uncer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine pittance of time that ſhall remaine; wherein, beſides your never enough thankefulneſſe for bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſings received, let the remembrance of your ſinnes bee bitter unto you; and caſt not away your Soule by faſhioning your ſelfe after this Phariſaicall and moſt ſinfull time; but, be holy, upright, uncorrupt, mercifull, peaceable; to ſhut up all in a word, la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:3192:15"/>by all meanes <hi>to have alwayes a cleare conſcience towards God and towards man,</hi> and never forget that all your actions how ſecret ſoever, or pharaſaically cloaked, ſhall in that great and fearfull day of ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compts be revealed. Wherefore in all your acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons remember your end, and ever bleſſe God, and beginne the day with a morning ſacrifice to him, and then he will bleſſe the day vnto you, and direct all your actions to the glory of his moſt ſacred name, the good of your country, and preſervation of your owne ſoules and bodies.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="section">
               <head>O Exerciſe and Reſt. SECT. 2.</head>
               <head type="sub">Why ought Students, and all ſuch as are ſtudious of health, and that lead a generous courſe of life, to have ſpeciall regard of exerciſe, and of avoiding immoderate reſt? And as touching exerciſe, that it may bee rightly uſed, how many things ought to be obſerved therein?</head>
               <p>EXerciſe is ſo neceſſary to the preſervation of health in Students, and all ſuch as live a reſtfull and generous life, as that without it they can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be long healthfull and without ſickneſſe:<note place="margin">The commodi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties of exerciſe, and the diſcom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modities of im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moderate reſt.</note> for by exerciſe and moderate motions, the naturall heat is encreaſed, the ſpirits excited and dilated, the conco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction and diſtribution holpen, the humours attenu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ated,
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:3192:16"/>the expulſion of all excrements furthered, the whole body ſtrengthned, and youth prolonged. Of the contrary, by immoderate and ſluggiſh reſt, the naturall heat is extinguiſhed, the concoction of the meats, and diſtribution to the parts hindred, the humours corrupted, the excrements retained, the whole body dulled and effeminated, infinite diſeaſes occaſioned, and old age haſtned, and all by reaſon of crudities, and great ſtore of noyſome humours thereby ingendred; and therefore idleneſſe and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moderate reſt is not unworthily ranked among the cauſes of cold diſeaſes. And this is found true by dayly experience in agreſticke men, and all ſuch as lead a laborious courſe of life, who for the more part live longer, and in better health and ſtrength, then they that live in bodily reſt, or enjoy a generous ſtate of living. Wherefore it is very behoveable for Students and all ſuch as lead not a laborious courſe of life, to ſupport by exerciſe and voluntary moti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons their health, and not by being too indulgent of their eaſe and reſt, infringe their ſtrengths, and ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vert their ſtate of body.</p>
               <p>But moderate reſt, and in convenient time obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved, hath alſo its commodities: for when the body is tired through over much labour, and ſtrength fai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth, and naturall moiſture decayeth, then reſt for a time recovereth ſtrength, reviveth the ſpirits, and refreſheth the limbes. So the mind wearied with cares and ſtudies hath need of remiſſion and relaxa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, without which gratefull viciſſitude, the vigor neither of mind nor body can long be preſerved, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to that of the Poet:
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:3192:16"/>
                  <q>Quod caret alterna requie, durabile non eſt.</q>
               </p>
               <p>Now that exerciſe may be rightly uſed for the health of the body,<note place="margin">Three things to bee obſerved in exerciſe.</note> three things are to bee obſerved therein: The Place, the Time, and the Meaſure. The place where exerciſe is to be uſed doth chiefly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerne the ayre, which muſt be cleare and pure, not vaporous or putride, which as in habitation, ſo alſo in exerciſe is greatly to be regarded: for the pores and paſſages of the body being open by exerciſe, the ambient ayre cannot but enter in, and be alſo, by reaſon of the violence of breathing, vehemently drawne to the heart, which if it ſhall be groſſe, vapo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rours, or impure, cannot but very greatly offend the head, breed rheumes, annoy the heart, and corrupt the whole body: wherefore it is not good to exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſe but in a good and wholeſome ayre.</p>
               <p>Now for the time fit for exerciſe, <hi>Hip.</hi> teacheth us plainly in three words, <hi>Labores cibum praecedant,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">The fitteſt time for exerciſe,</note> Let exerciſe be uſed before meat. The time then moſt convenient for exerciſe, muſt needs be when both the firſt and ſecond digeſtion is complete, and that the time approcheth to eate againe. But from the exerciſe to the eating there muſt alwayes intercede a little time of reſt, as halfe an houre or thereabout, eſpecially it the exerciſe be any thing violent, that the ſpirits and limbes may be refreſhed, and the hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mours in the body quieted and ſetled. Before exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſe this caution muſt alwayes very carefully be ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved,<note place="margin">A caution al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes carefully to be obſerved before exerciſe.</note> that the excrements of the belly and bladder be expulſed, that none of them by the violence of heat kindled by exerciſe, be drawne into the habite of the body, whereby the bloud may be corrupted,
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:3192:17"/>and very perilous obſtructions occaſioned. Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore it is not good to exerciſe before the meate pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aſſumed be well concocted, and the excrements of the belly and bladder carefully depoſed. I will not here reſtraine any to certaine houres of the day for exerciſe, but as their occaſions ſhall give leave, ſo as it be done according to theſe three rules, that is, After the excrements are avoided, In a wholeſome ayre, and before meat. Whereunto I will adde a fourth, And, not in the fervent heat of the day, <hi>Ne duplici calore afficiatur corpus,</hi> that the body be not at once affected with the outward heat of the ayre, and the inward heat of the body raiſed by exerciſe: wherefore in exerciſe let the fitneſſe of time be al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes obſerved.<note place="margin">The diſcom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modities of un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>timely exerciſe.</note> For untimely exerciſe doth greatly hurt the body, as to exerciſe immediately after meale, or before the meat be concocted, for thereby the naturall heat is drawne from the inward parts to the outward, the concoction conſequently marred, and the whole body repleted with crude and noy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome ſuperfluities. Hence proceed obſtructions, im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtumes, ſcabs, and oftentimes ulcers, as is to be ſeene in divers that unadviſedly labour or exerciſe immediately after meat, or before it be ſufficiently concocted.<note place="margin">VValking after meat very pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fitable.</note> Yet to riſe up after meat, to ſtand and to walke ſoftly is very good, for by this meanes the meates doe ſooner deſcend to the bottome of the ſtomacke, and the naturall heat is alſo ſomwhat ſtir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red vp, whereupon doth follow the ſpeedier and bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter concoction. Wherefore I cannot but very great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly commend walking after dinner in the Summer ſeaſon in a cold arbour, and after ſupper in the tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perate
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:3192:17"/>and hot ſeaſons of the yeare, in open plaine fields or in ſweet meadowes nigh to pleaſant rivers: for the digeſtion is not onely holpen thereby, but the ſpirits are alſo delighted, the whole body refre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed, and the fumes ariſing from the ſtomacke diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſſed. And if your ſtate of body be ſuch as that you cannot walke after meale, yet ſtand at leaſt, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the old verſe;
<q>Poſt paſtum ſtabis, paſſu mollive meabis.</q>
               </p>
               <p>To conclude this point, I doe here therefore counſell all ſtudents, and ſuch as live generouſly, to labour neither in body nor mind immediately after meat (for as of the body, ſo alſo of the mind ought the exerciſes to be ſeaſonable, for untimely ſtudies doe ſoone weaken the ſtrengths both of body and mind) but to ſpend an houre in gentle walkings, and pleaſant diſcourſe. And thus much concerning the time convenient for exerciſe.</p>
               <p>Now I come to the meaſure of exerciſe,<note place="margin">The meaſure of exerciſe, 1. how long we ſhould exerciſe.</note> a meane wherein, as in all other things, is beſt, which by two notes may chiefly be diſcerned: The firſt is by the burſting forth of ſweat, and hot vapours; the other, by the wearineſſe of the limbes: for when the skinne ſhall be wet with ſwear, it ſhall be good to deſiſt from exerciſe, leſt by proceeding therein,<note place="margin">The diſcommo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditie of immo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derate exerciſe.</note> not onely the ſpirits and good humours be exhauſted, but alſo the fat annexed to Liver, Reines, and Inteſtines, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by the naturall heat of thoſe parts is preſerved, bee melted, or at leaſt cauſed to putrifie; by meanes whereof, if ſudden death enſue not, as oftentimes it doth, the concoction is weakned, and the body be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come ſickly, withered, and imparient of cold. And
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:3192:18"/>when the agilitie of the limbes ſhall beginne to faile, it ſhall be good to deſiſt, leſt over-much wearineſſe and feebleneſſe ſhould enſue. Here therefore it is to be advertiſed, how great and laborious exerciſes doe evilly diſpoſe the body, and ſubvert the ſtate thereof, and that the beſt and moſt profitable exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſes, for them that are ſound and healthfull, are walking, bowling, <hi>Et parvae pilae ludus,</hi> the racket, and ſuch like eaſie exerciſes. For it is certaine, that for ſuch as are health full it is ſufficient by exerciſe to encreaſe the naturall heat, to excite the ſpirits, and expell the excrements, which the aforeſaid exerciſes doe well effect, without any great trouble or laſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude of the body. Wherefore the true meaſure of exerciſe is, not to be overwearied therewith, nor too ſuddenly to ſweat and raiſe the ſpirits. But a mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure in exerciſe cannot rightly be limited without reſpect had to the conſtitution and ſtate of body, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the phlegmaticke,<note place="margin">Phlegmaticke and groſſe bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies need oft<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner and ſtron<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger exerciſe then other.</note> and all ſuch as are of a full ſtate of body, require more often and more labori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous exerciſe then others, for exciting the naturall heat, diſcuſſing the ſuperfluous moiſture, and aba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting the groſſeneſſe of the body: for by how much fatter and groſſer the body is; by ſo much the natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall heat is diminiſhed. Wherefore for exciting the naturall heat, and diſſolving the ſuperfluous moi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſture of the body, which is the cauſe of groſſeneſſe, I adviſe the plegmaticke, and all ſuch as are apt to be groſſe, to accuſtome themſelves in the mornings to ſpeedy walkings, and that up againſt hils or other ſteepe places, and at other times convenient, to ſtrong and laborious exerciſes; yet with this cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:3192:18"/>therein, that they doe not ſo much exceed the meane, as to cauſe over-much wearineſſe and weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe to the body.</p>
               <p>Of the contrarie to the cholericke,<note place="margin">To leane and cholericke bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies eaſie and light exerciſe is convenient.</note> and all ſuch as are of a drye and leane ſtate of body, eaſie and light exerciſe is convenient, and that alſo no longer to be continued, but till the colour and fleſh is ſomewhat ruddy, and the ſweat beginnes to breake forth. For if they ſhould proceed further, or uſe more quicke and vehement motions, the ſpirits would bee ſoone exhauſted, the body diſtempered and brought into an Atrophy or Conſumption. They therefore that are of a very hot temperature, and of a leane and dry ſtate of body, ought not at any hand to uſe any ſtrong motions or exerciſe of body, but walking, bowling, and ſuch like eaſie motions are abundantly ſufficient for them.</p>
               <p>As touching exerciſe alſo,<note place="margin">The time of the yeare ought to be reſpected in the exerciſe.</note> the time of the yeare ought not altogether to be neglected, for in the ſum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer, by reaſon of the ambient heat of the ayre, ligh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter exerciſes are more convenient, then at other times. In the Spring the exerciſe ought to bee ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what ſtronger, that the ſuperfluities, which by rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of the winter are congeſted in the body, may be reſolued. But in this ſeaſon let ſuch as are of an hot temperature of body beware leſt by over-much mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion they over-heat and diſtemper it. But in the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tumne, and eſpecially in the winter, ſtrong and labo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious motion of the body is moſt convenient, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it diſſolveth and diſſipateth groſſe humours, helpeth the breathing, by removing the obſtructions of the breſt, occaſioned by the moiſture of the ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon,
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:3192:19"/>and is therefore ſpecially neceſſary and profita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble for groſſe and phlegmaticke bodies.</p>
               <p>I will conclude this Section by adding one cauti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to be obſerved after exerciſe, and which is of ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry great moment;<note place="margin">A eaution to be obſerved after exerciſe.</note> that is, that the body take not cold after the exerciſe, becauſe it greatly weakneth the naturall heat, the braine, and the ſinewes, and induceth oftentimes ſwoundings by a ſudden ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction of the pores, and barring in of vaporous moiſture that ſhould by them breathe forth. And thus much concerning the true uſe and utility of exerciſe.</p>
               <p>Now for thoſe that cannot exerciſe their bodies at convenient times, by reaſon of great weakneſſe, frication or rubbing of the body <hi>(Quae inter exerci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tationi et omni modam quietem media eſt.)</hi> may well be uſed in ſtead of exerciſe:<note place="margin">Frication, the neceſſity and utility thereof.</note> for it exciteth the natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall heat of the parts, openeth the obſtructions of the skinne and fleſh, draweth the humours from the ſuperiour parts to the inferior, from the inward to the outward, from the noble to the ignoble, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by great comfort and utility is brought to weak and ſickly bodies. Moreover it procureth ſleepe; but the belly and the ſtomacke muſt not be perfricated, becauſe it will trouble the concoction, offend the head, and occaſion the diſtribution of crudities into the body. The application of a double cloath vpon thoſe parts, well heated for the purpoſe, during all the time of frication is very neceſſary for the conſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation of the heat of thoſe parts, and diſcuſſing of wind. Neither muſt the reynes of the backe be rub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bed, unleſſe there be a ſenſible feeling of cold and
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:3192:19"/>winde in them, and then they muſt bee gently ſtro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked, leſt overheating them, obſtruction and nephri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticke paſſions bee occaſioned. The manner of uſing fricacies muſt bee with the hand, or a courſe linnen cloath; firſt, ſoftly and eaſily, afterwards faſter and harder, as the tenderneſſe of the skine ſhall permit, untill the fleſh ſhall as it were ſwell, and bee ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what ruddie: then deſiſt, for a mediocrity even in frication muſt bee obſerved. As for the time, the morning and evening are beſt for fricacies: and what parts are fitteſt for frication, I have ſhewed to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards the end of the precedent Section. To con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude, fricacies are very needfull and profitable for the aged, the impotent, and ſuch as are barred of exerciſe by reaſon of dayly and waighty buſineſſe.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="section">
               <head>Of Excretions. SECT. 3.</head>
               <head type="sub">Why doth the health of the body much conſiſt in the due and daily avoyding of the generall excrements?</head>
               <p>THE generall excrements of the body are the ſtoole, the urine, and the ſweat; and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they are altogether unprofitable, being excrements, not onely in quantity, but alſo in qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity, they ought every day, to the caſe and health of the body, to bee avoyded; for, being retained lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:3192:20"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="25" facs="tcp:3192:20"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="26" facs="tcp:3192:21"/>then is fitting, they become very troubleſome and pernicious to the body. Wherefore, ſuch as are ſtudious of their health, muſt bee very carefull daily and opportunely to avoide the excrements of the belly and bladder. And if your belly ſhall bee natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally ſoluble,<note place="margin">Health doth greatly conſiſt in a ſoluble belly.</note> account that in regard of your health, for a great felicity. For they that have their belly naturally looſe and open, ſo it bee not immoderate, and more then their ſtate of body, in regard of the groſeneſſe or tenuity thereof, ſhall require, are not eaſily affected with ſickneſſe: whereas, of the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary, they that have the ſame bound up, and have ſeldome the benefit of nature that way, have for the moſt part, often conflicts with ſickneſſe, I ſay for the moſt part, in regard of exceeding hot cholericke bodies, who, in regard of their ſtrong naturall heat, that concocteth with few ſuperfluities, have com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly coſtive bodies, and yet enjoy perfect and ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolute health. Wherefore I adviſe all ſuch as are ſtudious of their health, to have ſpeciall care that their belly expurge it ſelfe daily, twiſe or once at the leaſt.</p>
               <p>And how beneficiall it is for the health, to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure ſweat by exerciſe, I have ſhewed in the former Section; and therefore I ſhall not here neede much to inſiſt therein. Nature verely hath to no other pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe made the skinne full of pores, but that there ſhould bee free paſſage through it for ſweat and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenſible vaporations. I ſhall not here need to ſhew, that it is not convenient for very hot and dry bodies to provoke ſweat: or of the contrary, for cold, moiſt, and Phlegmaticke bodies very needfull; nor yet, in
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:3192:21"/>procuring of ſweat, that there muſt bee ſpeciall care had, as in all other kinds of evacuations, that it bee not immoderate, &amp; deject the ſtrengths, for all this is at large ſhewed in the former Section.</p>
               <p>Beſides theſe generall excrements, there are alſo particular, as thoſe of the braine, and breſt, which being retained, and not liberally excreted, doe great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly annoy and affect thoſe parts. Wherefore the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crements of the braine muſt daily bee avoyded through the mouth by ſpetting, and excreation, through the noſe by exſufflation, and alſo ſomtimes by ſternutation, eſpecially in the mornings; and thoſe of the breaſt by coughing expectorated. And thus much for excretions.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="section">
               <head>Of Perturbations, or Paſsi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons <hi>of the minde.</hi> SECT. 4.</head>
               <head type="sub">Seeing that the Paſsions of the minde are inevitable, <hi>&amp; ſecundum naturam nobis ſuccreſcant,</hi> why are they reputed as morbificall cauſes, and hurtfull to the Body?</head>
               <p>I Will nothere ſtand to diſcourſe of the objects of Perturbations, nor how the ſenſitive facultie is the fountaine of them; nor how they are the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turall motions of the heart, and that by meanes of
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:3192:22"/>the ſpirits, which are the primary inſtruments of the ſoul, as things altogether impertinent for this place; but how they are to bee reputed as morbificall cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, and hurtfull to the body.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Animi paſsiones dum intra modum conſiſtunt, &amp; ne<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> animam à conſuetis, &amp; naturali moderatione &amp; virtute dimovent, non animi perturbationes, ſed</hi> actus <hi>jure dicentur:</hi> and in this reſpect they are ſaid to be inevitable, <hi>&amp; ſecundam naturam nobis ſuccreſcere:</hi> to bee naturall, <hi>&amp; utiliter à natura dari.</hi> Theſe Paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions, <hi>Cicero: Leves perturbationes optimè dixit. Ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum cum modum exceſſerunt, &amp; hominis decentem harmoniam, &amp; elegantiam, ac modum naturali debi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum mutaverint, tunc quidem animi paſsiones ſeu per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turbationes jure optimo dicendae ſunt, &amp; vitandae, ut corpori &amp; animae, noxiae.</hi> The Paſſions therefore of the minde are not to bee reputed hurtfull, or num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bred among the cauſes of ſickneſſe, but when they ſhall exceed and bee imoderate, and ſo become per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turbations indeed: for then they alter the body, wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken and overthrow the faculties thereof. I will in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance in ſome:<note place="margin">Immoderate joy.</note> Immoderate joy relaxeth the heart, and cauſeth ſuch an effuſion of the ſpirit, as that of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentimes enſue fickneſs, and great debility of the body, ſowndings; and as wee read of ſome puſillani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>micke or faint hearted perſons,<note place="margin">Sadneſſe and feare.</note> death it ſelfe. Sad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes and Feare, of the contrary, do ſtreiten the heart, weaken the ſpirits, and naturall heate, and cauſe them to bee contracted to the heart, by meanes whereof, the digeſtion of the meats, and diſtributi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on is hindred, and the remote parts left deſtitute of heate: and from hence proceedeth that vacillation
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:3192:22"/>or trembling of the limbes in them that are affected with feare: Moreover, ſadneſs and feare, in conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuance, dry the body, reſolve the ſtrengths, preſſe the heart, and induce melancholicke ſickneſſes, by exciccating the blood and ſpirits neere the heart.</p>
               <p>Here ſome may demaund, that if trembling of the limbs proceed from the defect of heat in the parts, and if feare draw the heate and ſpirits inward, eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially to the heart, why the heart doth tremble in the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that are affected with feare? Whereunto it may bee anſwered, that although fear force the heat &amp; ſpirits inward, yet it compels them not to the heart ſtrong and lively, but weakened &amp; abated: <hi>Nam in metuen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tibus craſſeſcunt ſpiritus &amp; ſanguis, fiunt<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> imbecilliores frigore,</hi> and that by reaſon of the imagination, which is earneſtly bent and troubled in preventing and withſtanding the imminent miſchiefe and peril. And from hence it is that the heart is not onely ſtreitned, and doth tremble in feare, but alſo that many ſwound, die, and are exanimated with ſodaine fear, the heat and ſpirits being extinguiſhed by overmuch blood conglobated in the heart. <hi>Dum enim anima ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>more concutitur, ut vitae conſulat, ſanguinem &amp; ſpiritus cuſtodiae gratia repentè ad interiora &amp; ad cor praecipuè, quod corporis quaſi princeps eſt, invocat &amp; contrahit.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Anger ſtirreth up the natural heat,<note place="margin">Anger.</note> breedeth cho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler, and inflameth the blood and ſpirits. And here it is to be obſerved, that though Anger be reputed a morbificall cauſe, and hurtfull to the bodie; yet not alwaies and alike to all bodies: for to phlegmaticke bodies it is ſometimes very neceſſary to the preſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation of their health, becauſe the naturall heat, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:3192:23"/>therewith ſtirred up and encreaſed, doth the bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter concoct, diſcuſſe, and conſume their crude and moiſt ſuperfluities. The like may bee alſo ſaid of o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther perturbations; whence it is manifeſt, <hi>Animi paſsiones poſſe mutare corpus, &amp; affectus ejuſdem con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trarietate ſanare, &amp; ob id utiliter à natura dari.</hi> But Anger to all other, eſpecially to hot and dry bodies, is very hurtfull, becauſe it vehemently heateth the Bodie, drieth it, and reſolveth the ſtrengths.</p>
               <p>Wherefore, ſeeing that the affections and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turbations of the minde are of ſuch force for the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verthrowing of the health and welfare of the Bodie, I adviſe all ſuch,<note place="margin">Salubre conſili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um.</note> as are reſpective of their health, to bridle all irrationall motions of the minde by the reaſon and underſtanding, and labour by all meanes to obſerue a mediocritie in their paſſion, wherein conſiſteth the tranquility both of minde and body, which of this life is the chiefeſt happineſſe. To con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude this Section, and to adde a period to this worke; among all the affections of the minde, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ware chiefly of ſadneſſe, for it dryeth the bones; and embrace moderate joy, for both body and mind are bettered therby: and that your joy may be joy in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed, ſtrive, without halting, to enjoy with all the joy of a good conſcience, by living ſoberly, uprightly, and godly in this preſent world: <hi>Non enim habemus hîc manentem civitatem:</hi> For wee have here no con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinuing place of abode, but we ſeeke one to come, whoſe maker and builder is GOD; who, as <hi>Peter</hi> ſaith:<note place="margin">1 Cap. 2.9.</note> 
                  <hi>Hath called us out of darkeneſſe into his marve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous light, and deſtinated us to eternity.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="index">
            <pb facs="tcp:3192:23"/>
            <head>THE TABLE.</head>
            <list>
               <head>A.</head>
               <item>ANger, the effects thereof. <hi>Page.</hi> 29.</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>B.</head>
               <item>Belly, naturally ſoluble, great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly availeable to health. <hi>Page.</hi> 26.</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>E.</head>
               <item>Exerciſe, why muſt Students have a ſpecial regard thereof. <hi>Page.</hi> 17.</item>
               <item>The commodities of exerciſe. <hi>Page.</hi> 17.</item>
               <item>Three things to bee obſerved in exerciſe. <hi>Page.</hi> 19.</item>
               <item>The fitteſt time for exerciſe. <hi>Page.</hi> 19.</item>
               <item>A caution to bee obſerved be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore exerciſe, <hi>Page.</hi> 19.</item>
               <item>The diſcommodities of un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>timely exerciſe. <hi>Page.</hi> 20.</item>
               <item>The meaſure of exerciſe: 1, how long we ſhould exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſe. <hi>Page.</hi> 21.</item>
               <item>The diſcommodities of immo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derate exerciſe. <hi>Page.</hi> 21.</item>
               <item>Phlegmaticke &amp; groſſe bodies need oftner and ſtronger ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſe then other. <hi>Page.</hi> 22.</item>
               <item>To leane and cholericke bodies eaſie and light exerciſe is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venient. <hi>Page.</hi> 23.</item>
               <item>The time of the yeare ought to bee repected in exerciſe. <hi>Page.</hi> 23.</item>
               <item>A caution to be obſerved after exerciſe. <hi>Page.</hi> 24.</item>
               <item>Excrements, why doth the health of the body much con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſt in the due and daily a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voyding of them. <hi>Page.</hi> 2<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>F.</head>
               <item>Feare, the effects therof. <hi>Page.</hi> 28.</item>
               <item>Frication, the neceſſity and uti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity thereof. <hi>Page.</hi> 24.</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>I.</head>
               <item>Ioy, if immoderate, the effects thereof. <hi>Page.</hi> 28.</item>
               <item>Ioy, that it may bee ioy indeed. <hi>Page.</hi> 30.</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>P.</head>
               <item>Paſſions, or perturbations of the minde, ſeeing they are inevitable, <hi>&amp; ſecundum natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ram nobis ſuccreſcant,</hi> why are they reputed as morbificall cauſes and hurtful to the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy. <hi>Page.</hi> 27.</item>
               <item>Mediocrity in the Paſſion beſt. <hi>Page.</hi> 30.</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>S.</head>
               <item>Sadneſs, the effects thereof 28, moſt hurtfull of all affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons. <hi>Page.</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>0.</item>
               <item>Sleepe, that it may be taken for the health of the body, how many things ought ſuch as are ſtudious of their health to obſerve therein. <hi>Page.</hi> 2.</item>
               <item>Sleepe, the commodities
<pb facs="tcp:3192:24"/>thereof. <hi>Page.</hi> 1.</item>
               <item>The three principall faculties of the body are greatly holpen and refreſhed by ſleepe. <hi>Page.</hi> 2.</item>
               <item>The night, why moſt conveni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent for ſleepe. <hi>ibidem.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Three things neceſſary to quiet ſleepe. <hi>Page.</hi> 4.</item>
               <item>The great diſcommodity of mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning ſleepe. <hi>Page.</hi> 4.</item>
               <item>Sleeping at noones the diſcommo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dities thereof. <hi>Page.</hi> 5</item>
               <item>Sleeping at noones not to bee prohibited at all times, nor to all bodies. <hi>Page.</hi> 5</item>
               <item>Sleeping at noones, hurtfull to all corpulent bodies. <hi>Page.</hi> 6.</item>
               <item>Five conditions to bee obſerved in ſleeping at noones. <hi>Page.</hi> 6.</item>
               <item>What? place moſt convenient for ſleepe. <hi>Page.</hi> 7</item>
               <item>The head and necke in ſleep muſt carefully be defended from cold. <hi>Page.</hi> 7.</item>
               <item>What poſiture of the body is beſt in ſleepe. <hi>Page.</hi> 8</item>
               <item>VVhether ſleeping upright upon the backe or groveling upon the belly, be altogether unwhol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome. <hi>Page.</hi> 8.</item>
               <item>To ſleepe upon the belly, when and for what bodies profitable. <hi>Page.</hi> 9.</item>
               <item>Whether it be expedient to ſleep with the mouth a little open. <hi>Page.</hi> 9</item>
               <item>How long wee ſhould ſleep. <hi>Page.</hi> 10.</item>
               <item>Why doe cholericke and melan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cholicke bodies require longer ſleep then the phlegmaticke. <hi>Page.</hi> 12</item>
               <item>Little ſleep beſt for phlegmaticke and groſſe bodies. <hi>Page.</hi> 13.</item>
               <item>Why muſt the ſanguine bee very wary of immoderate ſleep. <hi>Page.</hi> 13.</item>
               <item>The diſcommodities of immode<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate ſleepe. <hi>Page.</hi> 13.</item>
               <item>What is to be done upon the ſleep for the health of the body. <hi>Page.</hi> 14.</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>R</head>
               <item>Rubbings of the head and necke mornings very effectuall againſt theumes, and cold infirmities of the ſinews. <hi>Page.</hi> 16.</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>W.</head>
               <item>Watchings, if immoderate, the hurts thereof. <hi>Page.</hi> 13.</item>
               <item>Vntimely watchings moſt pernici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous to ſtudents. <hi>Page.</hi> 3.</item>
            </list>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:3192:24"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
